<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.0/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	article-type="editorial" dtd-version="1.0" specific-use="sps-1.6" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<journal-meta>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abc</journal-id>
			<journal-title-group>
				<journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Arq. Bras.
					Cardiol.</abbrev-journal-title>
			</journal-title-group>
			<issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
			<issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia - SBC</publisher-name>
			</publisher>
		</journal-meta>
		<article-meta>
			<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20170100</article-id>
			<article-categories>
				<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
					<subject>Editorial</subject>
				</subj-group>
			</article-categories>
			<title-group>
				<article-title>Blood Pressure Targets: Will We Reach Definite Figures? I Currently
					Have Mine</article-title>
			</title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Jardim</surname>
						<given-names>Paulo César B. Veiga</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
					<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
				</contrib>
				<aff id="aff1">
					<institution content-type="orgname">Universidade Federal de Goiás</institution>
					<institution content-type="orgdiv1">Faculdade de Medicina</institution>
					<institution content-type="orgdiv2">Liga de Hipertensão Arterial</institution>
					<addr-line>
						<named-content content-type="city">Goiânia</named-content>
						<named-content content-type="state">GO</named-content>
					</addr-line>
					<country country="BR">Brazil</country>
					<institution content-type="original">Faculdade de Medicina Universidade Federal
						de Goiás (UFG); Pós-graduação em Ciências da Saúde e Nutrição em Saúde da
						UFG; Liga de Hipertensão Arterial da UFG, Goiânia, GO - Brazil</institution>
					<institution content-type="normalized">Universidade Federal de
						Goiás</institution>
				</aff>
			</contrib-group>
			<author-notes>
				<corresp id="c1"><bold>Mailing Address: Paulo César B. Veiga Jardim,</bold> Rua
					115-F n 135, Setor Sul. Postal Code 74085-300, Goiania, GO - Brazil. E-mail:
						<email>fvjardim.ufg@gmail.com</email>, <email>fvjardim@terra.com.br</email>
				</corresp>
			</author-notes>
			<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
				<month>07</month>
				<year>2017</year>
			</pub-date>
			<volume>109</volume>
			<issue>1</issue>
			<fpage>01</fpage>
			<lpage>04</lpage>
			<permissions>
				<license license-type="open-access"
					xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xml:lang="en">
					<license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
						Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
						distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
						properly cited.</license-p>
				</license>
			</permissions>
			<kwd-group xml:lang="en">
				<title>Keywords</title>
				<kwd>Hypertension</kwd>
				<kwd>Blood Pressure / physiology</kwd>
				<kwd>Antihypertensive Agents</kwd>
				<kwd>Diabetes Mellitus</kwd>
				<kwd>Blood Pressure Targets</kwd>
			</kwd-group>
		</article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
		<p>I was born before the era of evidence-based Medicine. When I was a student, arterial
			hypertension (AH) used to be diagnosed based on blood pressure (BP) readings greater
			than 160/95 mm Hg.</p>
		<p>Can anyone imagine that now?</p>
		<p>Cardiology has advanced a lot in all directions, both in diagnostic and treatment
			methods. Currently, treatment is based on scientific evidence, and the drug
			armamentarium available is extremely effective.</p>
		<p>But let us go back to AH.</p>
		<p>Over the years, we have learned through a large number of studies, initially
			observational ones, and then intervention ones, that, if on the one side cardiovascular
			risk increases with BP levels from 115/75 mm Hg on, doubling with every 20-mmHg increase
			in systolic BP (SBP) and 10-mmHg increase in diastolic BP (DBP), on the other,
			cardiovascular risk decreases significantly with BP reduction by using the
			pharmacological treatment offered to hypertensives.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
				>1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
		<p>There is no definite evidence that non-pharmacological treatment (healthy lifestyle)
			yields the same results, but that is an obvious universally accepted assumption,
			although difficult to implement nowadays.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
				>1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
		<p>Excellent antihypertensive agents have been developed and perfected. The benefits of
			their use regarding both morbidity and mortality have been proven.<xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
		<p>There is no doubt about that.</p>
		<p>We face, however, some dilemmas, beginning with access to healthcare services and
			medications, when required. That is crucial, depends on consistent public policies that
			change the <italic>status quo</italic>; nevertheless, that is not the object of this
				discussion.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B5">5</xref></p>
		<p>Another aspect, concerning treatment itself, is the huge challenge posed by adherence to
			treatment. Currently, a small number of individuals, aware of their hypertensive
			condition and of the risks inherent to it, and even having access to the healthcare
			system, do not adhere to the proposed treatment. This critical issue involves
			educational measures as the major tool for that behavior change, which is common and
			universal, but, once again, this is not the object of my observations today.<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"
			>5</xref></p>
		<p>Moving on to what matters!</p>
		<p>In the past 40 years, hundreds of studies on the treatment of AH were conducted
			worldwide, providing us with the opportunity to find that pharmacological therapy
			modifies the natural history of AH, significantly reducing cardiovascular mortality and
			morbidity. It is worth noting that this fact is rather due mainly to BP reduction, than
			to the type of drug used.</p>
		<p>Therefore, the epidemiological cycle is closed: BP reduction is effectively
				beneficial.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B5">5</xref></p>
		<p>But how much should it be reduced? To which extent is it safe?</p>
		<p>The dilemma of targets!</p>
		<p>Most studies showing a reduction in cardiovascular events have been designed to compare
			BP levels before and after treatment. At first, active drugs were compared to placebo,
			assessing the changes in BP and its possible benefits. Later, active drugs have been
			compared to each other, aiming at finding differences between them.</p>
		<p>The major focus was not the BP reached, but the difference between initial and final
			levels.</p>
		<p>The best source of evidence in medicine is known to come from randomized controlled
			clinical trials. Establishing objective targets required the investigation design to
			have that purpose.</p>
		<p>The HOT (<italic>Hypertension Optimal Treatment</italic>) study,<xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B6">6</xref> published in 1998, was a pioneer in regard to targets, DBP being
			the reference used. Over 18500 patients aged between 50 and 80 years (mean, 61.5 years),
			with DBP between 100 and 115 mmHg, were allocated to DBP targets of &#x2264; 90 mm Hg,
			&#x2264; 85 mmHg and &#x2264; 80 mmHg. As DBP levels lowered, greater reductions in
			cardiovascular events were observed, the greater benefit occurring in the group of
			patients whose DBP was reduced to the mean level of 82.6 mm Hg. Reductions to levels
			below those were observed to be safe, and, among patients with diabetes, the benefits
			were even higher for the group whose target was DBP &#x2264; 80 mmHg. That study was a
			landmark regarding BP targets, and international guidelines have based their
			recommendation on it for years.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"
			>6</xref></p>
		<p>Over time, there have been hundreds of good quality investigations on drug interventions,
			involving thousands of patients, and they have continued to support the benefits of BP
			control; however, the ones assessing targets have been scarce.<xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"
				>4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></p>
		<p>Many might be thinking on some studies aimed at establishing some targets, such as the
			Italian Cardio-Sis, published in 2009, that investigated non-diabetic hypertensives over
			the age of 55 years, and aimed at SBP targets &lt; 130 mmHg or &lt; 140 mmHg. In that
			study, the intermediate primary outcome ‘left ventricular hypertrophy’ showed
			significantly favorable results for lower BP levels, and positive results regarding
			pre-specified secondary outcomes, which were cardiovascular.<xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B7">7</xref></p>
		<p>Similarly, in 2008, the CASE-J trial, involving only elderly individuals, was published
			reporting significant advantages for lower BP levels. In addition, in 2008, the JATOS
			study, assessing elderly, showed no difference between SBP targets under 140 mm Hg or
			160 mm Hg.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">8</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B9">9</xref></p>
		<p>Until then, all official documents, including our last guideline, assessing what BP
			levels should be pursued for greater benefits, had worked with BP under 140/90 mmHg for
			the general population, and under 130/80 mmHg for individuals at high cardiovascular
			risk, those with cardiovascular disease, diabetes and established kidney disease.<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4"
				>4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref><sup>,</sup><xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">11</xref></p>
		<p>In 2010, the result of the ACCORD study was published.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"
				>12</xref> It assessed only patients with diabetes, and tried to define if stricter
			BP control targets (SBP &lt; 120 mmHg) was advantageous over conventional targets (SBP
			&lt; 140 mmHg). That study randomized more than 4500 diabetic hypertensives, with a mean
			age of 62 years, followed up for a mean period of 4.7 years. The primary composite
			outcome was non-fatal myocardial infarction, non-fatal stroke or cardiovascular death.
			In addition, several secondary cardiocirculatory outcomes were predefined. The results
			were null, that is, there was no difference in major, fatal and non-fatal cardiovascular
			combined events. Regarding secondary outcomes, there was no significant difference,
			except for fatal and non-fatal stroke, which showed a significant reduction of 41% and
			37%, respectively. The group with a more marked BP reduction had more adverse events,
			but without jeopardizing the end of the study.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"
			>12</xref></p>
		<p>That study had a huge repercussion, leading to a new rationale, which, in my opinion, was
				mistaken.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref> It was implied, almost immediately,
			that stricter BP targets for diabetic patients would be harmful, and, indirectly there
			was controversy about lower BP targets for all types of patients.<xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B5">5</xref></p>
		<p>I assess the ACCORD study findings and interpret its results differently. The primary
			outcomes were similar, that is, there was no difference.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"
				>12</xref> I emphasize the significance of that: there was neither reduction, nor
			increase in primary events.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref></p>
		<p>On the other hand, but not less important, assessing the secondary outcome ‘stroke’, we
			observe that there were benefits for the group with stricter BP control.<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> Who does not want to protect a diabetic patient
			from a stroke? Just food for thought!</p>
		<p>In the sequence of the investigations for more adequate BP levels, by the end of 2015,
			the SPRINT study was published.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref> Financed by the
			National Institutes of Health (NIH), without any conflict of interest, the protocol was
			carefully designed specifically aimed at assessing the more beneficial BP levels in
			terms of cardiocirculatory outcomes for non-diabetic hypertensives. Individuals aged 50
			years or older, with SBP between 130 and 180 mm Hg and at increased cardiovascular risk
			were selected. For individuals randomized for intensive treatment, a SBP target &lt; 120
			mmHg was defined, while for those randomized for standard treatment, a SBP target &lt;
			140 mmHg was defined. The primary composite outcome comprised acute myocardial
			infarction, other acute coronary syndromes, stroke, heart failure and death from
			cardiovascular causes. The secondary outcomes were defined as the individual components
			of primary outcome, all-cause death and the addition of primary outcome or all-cause
				death.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></p>
		<p>That study randomly assigned 9361 patients, more than 4650 to each treatment type. The
			mean age was 67.9 years, and the groups were homogeneous in all aspects. In the first
			year of follow-up, the mean SBP and DBP achieved were, respectively, 121.4 and 68.7 mm
			Hg in the intensive-treatment group, and 136.2 and 76.3 mm Hg in the standard-treatment
			group. At the end of the study, the mean SBP levels were 121.5 and 134.6 mm Hg in the
			intensive-treatment and standard-treatment groups, respectively.<xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B13">13</xref></p>
		<p>The SPRINT study, planned to last 5 years, was interrupted by the Safety Committee at
			3.26 years, because a significant difference in outcomes was observed between the groups
			on two pre-established occasions for such control. The intensive-treatment group showed
			a 25%-reduction in primary outcomes, and that difference began to appear from the first
			year of intervention on. The number of all-cause deaths was also 27% lower in that
			group, in which there were 43% less deaths from cardiovascular causes. Adverse events
			were more frequent in that group with stricter BP control, however without significant
			hindrance to the ongoing research.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></p>
		<p>That clinical trial was outstanding, had an excellent design, clear objectives and proper
			development. Its results were categorical. However, as any protocol, it is liable to be
			challenged, although, in that particular case, most lacked consistency.</p>
		<p>One point raised was its early interruption.</p>
		<p>But, how not to do that?</p>
		<p>It was a matter of safety. How can we not offer the best to our patients? In addition, on
			a critical review of the study, its results cannot be challenged for that reason. In
			fact, the trial effectively provided valuable information on the BP targets to be
			pursued.</p>
		<p>A good alternative to randomized clinical trials to confirm scientific evidence is
			provided by meta-analyses and systematic reviews. However, their results can be
			challenged, depending on the criteria used for selecting the studies to be assessed and
			those that should be eventually included.</p>
		<p>Regarding BP targets, there is a reasonable number of meta-analyses and systematic
			reviews on the subject.</p>
		<p>Four recent studies on that subject are worth noting: the first dates from 2015,
			assessing type 2 diabetic patients; two were from 2016, one by Xie et al.<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">16</xref> and the other by Ettehad et al.,<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">15</xref> both treating hypertensives in general; and the
			fourth, published in 2017 in the JACC, approached the same question in elderly
				patients.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">17</xref> All studies showed the benefits
			of stricter BP control to reduce cardiovascular morbidity and mortality in those
				patients.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr"
				rid="B17">17</xref></p>
		<p>In addition, it is worth emphasizing the interesting editorial by Perkovic and
				Rodgers<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref> published in the NEJM in November
			2015, concomitantly with the SPRINT study publication. In that editorial, the authors
			assessed the ACCORD and SPRINT studies together, identified their similarities and
			differences, and understood them as complementary, creating a new situation, with an
			even larger number of patients, and suggested additional results. Those authors reported
			that, although both studies had the same BP target and similar outcomes, the ACCORD
			study had a smaller statistical power and primary outcomes less-sensitive to BP changes
			as compared to those of the SPRINT study (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f1">Figure
			1</xref>). Those authors have not objectively suggested BP levels, but indicated, based
			on their observations and convictions, that stricter BP targets are welcome, mainly for
			individuals at higher cardiovascular risk.</p>
		<p>
			<fig id="f1">
				<label>Figure 1</label>
				<caption>
					<title>Combination of the outcomes of the SPRINT and ACCORD studies, and
						combined data of both studies. AMI: acute myocardial infarction; CE:
						coronary events; HF: heart failure; CV: cardiovascular. Adapted from
						Perkovic e Rodgers.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref></title>
				</caption>
				<graphic xlink:href="0066-782X-abc-109-01-0001-gf01.tif"/>
			</fig>
		</p>
		<p>At the beginning of 2017, Chobanian published in the JAMA a viewpoint that coincides with
			my understanding.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref> Its rationale is logical and
			based on the existing evidence. That author suggested even stricter targets (BP &lt;
			120/80 mmHg) for individuals under the age of 50 years. He values DBP for that age
			group, emphasizing the concept of the importance of DBP for youngsters. He suggested BP
			levels below 130 mmHg for individuals aged between 50 and 74 years at high
			cardiovascular risk or with established disease, including those with diabetes,
			considering the benefits reported in the ACCORD study regarding stroke. Finally, he
			recommended BP levels &lt;140 mmHg for all patients aged 75 years or older.<xref
				ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref></p>
		<p>Even considering the lack of definitive information on BP levels to be pursued in
			patients at high cardiovascular risk, inferring that excessively low BP levels can be
				harmful,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref> those are the figures I have been
			working with, taking each patient’s characteristics into consideration.</p>
		<p>Finally, it is worth noting that most individuals maintain BP levels far above any
			established BP target, and accepting higher BP levels is harmful, and will represent
			over the years a significant recrudescence of cardiovascular diseases, currently a major
			cause of morbidity and mortality.</p>
	</body>
	<back>
		<ref-list>
			<title>References</title>
			<ref id="B1">
				<label>1</label>
				<mixed-citation>Malachias MV, Souza WK, Plavnik FL, Brandão AA, Neves MF, et al;
					Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia. 7a Diretriz Brasileira de hipertensão
					arterial. Arq Bras Cardiol. 2016;107(3 supl 3):1-83.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Malachias</surname>
							<given-names>MV</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Souza</surname>
							<given-names>WK</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Plavnik</surname>
							<given-names>FL</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Brandão</surname>
							<given-names>AA</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Neves</surname>
							<given-names>MF</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
						<collab>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>7a Diretriz Brasileira de hipertensão arterial</article-title>
					<source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
					<year>2016</year>
					<volume>107</volume>
					<issue>3</issue>
					<supplement>supl Suppl 3</supplement>
					<fpage>1</fpage>
					<lpage>83</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B2">
				<label>2</label>
				<mixed-citation>Mancia G, Fagard R, Narkiewicz K, Redon J, Zanchetti A, Böhm M, et
					al. 2013 ESH/ESC guidelines for the management of arterial hypertension: the
					Task Force for the management of arterial hypertension of the European Society
					of Hypertension (ESH) and of the European Society of Cardiology (ESC). Eur Heart
					J. 2013;34(28):2159-219.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Mancia</surname>
							<given-names>G</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Fagard</surname>
							<given-names>R</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Narkiewicz</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Redon</surname>
							<given-names>J</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Zanchetti</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Böhm</surname>
							<given-names>M</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>2013 ESH/ESC guidelines for the management of arterial
						hypertension: the Task Force for the management of arterial hypertension of
						the European Society of Hypertension (ESH) and of the European Society of
						Cardiology (ESC)</article-title>
					<source>Eur Heart J</source>
					<year>2013</year>
					<volume>34</volume>
					<issue>28</issue>
					<fpage>2159</fpage>
					<lpage>2219</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B3">
				<label>3</label>
				<mixed-citation>Weber MA, Schiffrin EL, White WB, Mann S, Lindholm LH, Kenerson JG,
					et al. Clinical practice guidelines for the management of hypertension in the
					community: a statement by the American Society of Hypertension and the
					International Society of Hypertension. J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich).
					2014;16(1):14-26.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Weber</surname>
							<given-names>MA</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Schiffrin</surname>
							<given-names>EL</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>White</surname>
							<given-names>WB</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Mann</surname>
							<given-names>S</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Lindholm</surname>
							<given-names>LH</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Kenerson</surname>
							<given-names>JG</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Clinical practice guidelines for the management of hypertension
						in the community: a statement by the American Society of Hypertension and
						the International Society of Hypertension</article-title>
					<source>J Clin Hypertens (Greenwich)</source>
					<year>2014</year>
					<volume>16</volume>
					<issue>1</issue>
					<fpage>14</fpage>
					<lpage>26</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B4">
				<label>4</label>
				<mixed-citation>Daskalopoulou SS, Rabi DM, Zarnke KB, Dasgupta K, Nerenberg K,
					Cloutier L, et al. The 2015 Canadian Hypertension Education Program
					recommendations for blood pressure measurement, diagnosis, assessment of risk,
					prevention, and treatment of hypertension. Can J Cardiol.
					2015;31(5):549-68.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Daskalopoulou</surname>
							<given-names>SS</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Rabi</surname>
							<given-names>DM</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Zarnke</surname>
							<given-names>KB</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Dasgupta</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Nerenberg</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Cloutier</surname>
							<given-names>L</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>The 2015 Canadian Hypertension Education Program recommendations
						for blood pressure measurement, diagnosis, assessment of risk, prevention,
						and treatment of hypertension</article-title>
					<source>Can J Cardiol</source>
					<year>2015</year>
					<volume>31</volume>
					<issue>5</issue>
					<fpage>549</fpage>
					<lpage>568</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B5">
				<label>5</label>
				<mixed-citation>James PA, Oparil S, Carter BL, Cushman WC, Dennison-Himmelfarb C,
					Handler J, et al. 2014 Evidence-based guideline for the management of high blood
					pressure in adults report from the panel members appointed to the Eighth Joint
					National Committee (JNC 8). JAMA. 2014;311(5):507-20. Erratum in: JAMA.
					2014;311(17):1809.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>James</surname>
							<given-names>PA</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Oparil</surname>
							<given-names>S</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Carter</surname>
							<given-names>BL</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Cushman</surname>
							<given-names>WC</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Dennison-Himmelfarb</surname>
							<given-names>C</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Handler</surname>
							<given-names>J</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>2014 Evidence-based guideline for the management of high blood
						pressure in adults report from the panel members appointed to the Eighth
						Joint National Committee (JNC 8)</article-title>
					<source>JAMA</source>
					<year>2014</year>
					<volume>311</volume>
					<issue>5</issue>
					<fpage>507</fpage>
					<lpage>520</lpage>
					<comment>Erratum in: JAMA. 2014;311(17):1809.</comment>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B6">
				<label>6</label>
				<mixed-citation>Hansson L, Zanchetti A, Carruthers SG, Dahlöf B, Elmfeldt D, Julius
					S, et al. Effects of intensive blood-pressure lowering and low-dose aspirin in
					patients with hypertension: principal results of the Hypertension Optimal
					Treatment (HOT) randomised trial. HOT StudyGroup. Lancet.
					1998;351(9118):1755-62.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Hansson</surname>
							<given-names>L</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Zanchetti</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Carruthers</surname>
							<given-names>SG</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Dahlöf</surname>
							<given-names>B</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Elmfeldt</surname>
							<given-names>D</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Julius</surname>
							<given-names>S</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Effects of intensive blood-pressure lowering and low-dose aspirin
						in patients with hypertension: principal results of the Hypertension Optimal
						Treatment (HOT) randomised trial. HOT StudyGroup</article-title>
					<source>Lancet</source>
					<year>1998</year>
					<volume>351</volume>
					<issue>9118</issue>
					<fpage>1755</fpage>
					<lpage>1762</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B7">
				<label>7</label>
				<mixed-citation>Verdecchia P, Staessen JA, Angeli F, de Simone G, Achilli A, Ganau
					A, et al; Cardio-Sis Investigators. Usual versus tight control o of systolic
					blood pressure in non-diabetic patients with hypertension (Cardio-Sis) an
					open-label randomized trial. Lancet. 2009;374(9689):525-33. Erratum in: Lancet.
					2009;374(9693):880.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Verdecchia</surname>
							<given-names>P</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Staessen</surname>
							<given-names>JA</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Angeli</surname>
							<given-names>F</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>de Simone</surname>
							<given-names>G</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Achilli</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Ganau</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
						<collab>Cardio-Sis Investigators</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Usual versus tight control o of systolic blood pressure in
						non-diabetic patients with hypertension (Cardio-Sis) an open-label
						randomized trial</article-title>
					<source>Lancet</source>
					<year>2009</year>
					<volume>374</volume>
					<issue>9689</issue>
					<fpage>525</fpage>
					<lpage>533</lpage>
					<comment>Erratum in: Lancet. 2009;374(9693):880.</comment>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B8">
				<label>8</label>
				<mixed-citation>Ogihara T, Nakao K, Fukui T, Fukiyama K, Fujimoto A, Ueshima K, et
					al; CASE-J Trial Group. The optimal target blood pressure for antihypertensive
					treatment in Japanese elderly patients with high-risk hypertension: a
					subanalysis of the Candesartan Antihypertensive Survival Evaluation in Japan
					(CASE-J) trial. Hypertens Res. 2008;31(8):1595-601.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Ogihara</surname>
							<given-names>T</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Nakao</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Fukui</surname>
							<given-names>T</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Fukiyama</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Fujimoto</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Ueshima</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
						<collab>CASE-J Trial Group</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>The optimal target blood pressure for antihypertensive treatment
						in Japanese elderly patients with high-risk hypertension: a subanalysis of
						the Candesartan Antihypertensive Survival Evaluation in Japan (CASE-J)
						trial</article-title>
					<source>Hypertens Res</source>
					<year>2008</year>
					<volume>31</volume>
					<issue>8</issue>
					<fpage>1595</fpage>
					<lpage>1601</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B9">
				<label>9</label>
				<mixed-citation>JATOS Study Group. Principal results of the Japanese trial to assess
					optimal systolic blood pressure in elderly hypertensive patients (JATOS).
					Hypertens Res. 2008;31(12):2115-27.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<collab>JATOS Study Group</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Principal results of the Japanese trial to assess optimal
						systolic blood pressure in elderly hypertensive patients
						(JATOS)</article-title>
					<source>Hypertens Res</source>
					<year>2008</year>
					<volume>31</volume>
					<issue>12</issue>
					<fpage>2115</fpage>
					<lpage>2127</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B10">
				<label>10</label>
				<mixed-citation>Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention,
					Detection, Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure. [NIH Publication
					No. 04-5230]. Bethesda (MR): National High Blood Pressure Education Program;
					2004. (Report n° 5230).</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="book">
					<source>Seventh Report of the Joint National Committee on Prevention, Detection,
						Evaluation, and Treatment of High Blood Pressure</source>
					<comment>NIH Publication No. 04-5230</comment>
					<publisher-loc>Bethesda (MR)</publisher-loc>
					<publisher-name>National High Blood Pressure Education Program</publisher-name>
					<year>2004</year>
					<comment>Report n° 5230</comment>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B11">
				<label>11</label>
				<mixed-citation>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia; Sociedade Brasileira de
					Hipertensão; Sociedade Brasileira de Nefrologia. [VI Brazilian Guidelines on
					Hypertension]. Arq Bras Cardiol. 2010;95(1 Suppl):1-51. Erratum in: Arq Bras
					Cardiol. 2010;95(4):553.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<collab>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia</collab>
						<collab>Sociedade Brasileira de Hipertensão</collab>
						<collab>Sociedade Brasileira de Nefrologia</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>VI Brazilian Guidelines on Hypertension</article-title>
					<source>Arq Bras Cardiol</source>
					<year>2010</year>
					<volume>95</volume>
					<issue>1</issue>
					<supplement>Suppl</supplement>
					<fpage>1</fpage>
					<lpage>51</lpage>
					<comment>Erratum in: Arq Bras Cardiol. 2010;95(4):553.</comment>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B12">
				<label>12</label>
				<mixed-citation>Cushman WC, Evans GW, Byington RP, Goff DC Jr, Grimm RH Jr, Cutler
					JA, et al; ACCORD Study Group. Effects of intensive blood-pressure control in
					type 2 diabetes mellitus. N Engl J Med. 2010;362(17):1575-85.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Cushman</surname>
							<given-names>WC</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Evans</surname>
							<given-names>GW</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Byington</surname>
							<given-names>RP</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Goff</surname>
							<given-names>DC</given-names>
							<suffix>Jr</suffix>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Grimm</surname>
							<given-names>RH</given-names>
							<suffix>Jr</suffix>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Cutler</surname>
							<given-names>JA</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
						<collab>ACCORD Study Group</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Effects of intensive blood-pressure control in type 2 diabetes
						mellitus</article-title>
					<source>N Engl J Med</source>
					<year>2010</year>
					<volume>362</volume>
					<issue>17</issue>
					<fpage>1575</fpage>
					<lpage>1585</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B13">
				<label>13</label>
				<mixed-citation>Wright JT Jr, Williamson JD, Whelton PK, Snyder JK, Sink KM, Rocco
					MV, et al; SPRINT Research Group. A randomized trial of Intensive versus
					standard blood-pressure control. N Engl J Med.
					2015;373(22):2103-16.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Wright</surname>
							<given-names>JT</given-names>
							<suffix>Jr</suffix>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Williamson</surname>
							<given-names>JD</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Whelton</surname>
							<given-names>PK</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Snyder</surname>
							<given-names>JK</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Sink</surname>
							<given-names>KM</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Rocco</surname>
							<given-names>MV</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
						<collab>SPRINT Research Group</collab>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>A randomized trial of Intensive versus standard blood-pressure
						control</article-title>
					<source>N Engl J Med</source>
					<year>2015</year>
					<volume>373</volume>
					<issue>22</issue>
					<fpage>2103</fpage>
					<lpage>2116</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B14">
				<label>14</label>
				<mixed-citation>Emdin CA, Rahimi K, Neal B, Callender T, Perkovic V, Patel A. Blood
					pressure lowering in type 2 diabetes: a systematic review and meta-analysis.
					JAMA. 2015;313(6):603-15.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Emdin</surname>
							<given-names>CA</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Rahimi</surname>
							<given-names>K</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Neal</surname>
							<given-names>B</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Callender</surname>
							<given-names>T</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Perkovic</surname>
							<given-names>V</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Patel</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Blood pressure lowering in type 2 diabetes: a systematic review
						and meta-analysis</article-title>
					<source>JAMA</source>
					<year>2015</year>
					<volume>313</volume>
					<issue>6</issue>
					<fpage>603</fpage>
					<lpage>615</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B15">
				<label>15</label>
				<mixed-citation>Ettehad D, Emdin CA, Kiran A, Anderson SG, Callender T, Emberson J,
					et al. Blood pressure lowering for prevention of cardiovascular disease and
					death: a systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet.
					2016;387(10022):957-67.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Ettehad</surname>
							<given-names>D</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Emdin</surname>
							<given-names>CA</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Kiran</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Anderson</surname>
							<given-names>SG</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Callender</surname>
							<given-names>T</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Emberson</surname>
							<given-names>J</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Blood pressure lowering for prevention of cardiovascular disease
						and death: a systematic review and meta-analysis</article-title>
					<source>Lancet</source>
					<year>2016</year>
					<volume>387</volume>
					<issue>10022</issue>
					<fpage>957</fpage>
					<lpage>967</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B16">
				<label>16</label>
				<mixed-citation>Xie X, Atkins E, Lv J, Bennett A, Neal B, Ninomiya T, et al. Effects
					of intensive blood pressure lowering on cardiovascular and renal outcomes:
					updated systematic review and meta-analysis. Lancet.
					2016;387(10017):435-43.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Xie</surname>
							<given-names>X</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Atkins</surname>
							<given-names>E</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Lv</surname>
							<given-names>J</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Bennett</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Neal</surname>
							<given-names>B</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Ninomiya</surname>
							<given-names>T</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Effects of intensive blood pressure lowering on cardiovascular
						and renal outcomes: updated systematic review and
						meta-analysis</article-title>
					<source>Lancet</source>
					<year>2016</year>
					<volume>387</volume>
					<issue>10017</issue>
					<fpage>435</fpage>
					<lpage>443</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B17">
				<label>17</label>
				<mixed-citation>Bavishi C, Bangalore S, Messerli FH. Outcomes of intensive blood
					pressure lowering in older hypertensive patients. J Am Coll Cardiol.
					2017;69(5):486-93.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Bavishi</surname>
							<given-names>C</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Bangalore</surname>
							<given-names>S</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Messerli</surname>
							<given-names>FH</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Outcomes of intensive blood pressure lowering in older
						hypertensive patients</article-title>
					<source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
					<year>2017</year>
					<volume>69</volume>
					<issue>5</issue>
					<fpage>486</fpage>
					<lpage>493</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B18">
				<label>18</label>
				<mixed-citation>Perkovic V, Rodgers A. Redefining blood-pressure targets - SPRINT
					Starts the marathon. N Engl J Med. 2015;373(22):2175-8.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Perkovic</surname>
							<given-names>V</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Rodgers</surname>
							<given-names>A</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Redefining blood-pressure targets - SPRINT Starts the
						marathon</article-title>
					<source>N Engl J Med</source>
					<year>2015</year>
					<volume>373</volume>
					<issue>22</issue>
					<fpage>2175</fpage>
					<lpage>2178</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B19">
				<label>19</label>
				<mixed-citation>Chobanian AV. Hypertension in 2017 - what is the right target? JAMA.
					2017;317(6):579-80.</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Chobanian</surname>
							<given-names>AV</given-names>
						</name>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Hypertension in 2017 - what is the right target?</article-title>
					<source>JAMA</source>
					<year>2017</year>
					<volume>317</volume>
					<issue>6</issue>
					<fpage>579</fpage>
					<lpage>580</lpage>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
			<ref id="B20">
				<label>20</label>
				<mixed-citation>Böhm M, Schumacher H, Teo KK, Lonn EM, Mahfoud F, Mann JF, et al.
					Achieved blood pressure and cardiovascular outcomes in high-risk patients:
					results from ONTARGET and TRANSCEND trials. Lancet. 2017 Apr 5. [Epub ahead of
					print].</mixed-citation>
				<element-citation publication-type="journal">
					<person-group person-group-type="author">
						<name>
							<surname>Böhm</surname>
							<given-names>M</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Schumacher</surname>
							<given-names>H</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Teo</surname>
							<given-names>KK</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Lonn</surname>
							<given-names>EM</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Mahfoud</surname>
							<given-names>F</given-names>
						</name>
						<name>
							<surname>Mann</surname>
							<given-names>JF</given-names>
						</name>
						<etal/>
					</person-group>
					<article-title>Achieved blood pressure and cardiovascular outcomes in high-risk
						patients: results from ONTARGET and TRANSCEND trials</article-title>
					<source>Lancet</source>
					<day>05</day>
					<month>04</month>
					<year>2017</year>
					<comment>Epub ahead of print</comment>
				</element-citation>
			</ref>
		</ref-list>
	</back>
	<sub-article article-type="translation" id="s1" xml:lang="pt">
		<front-stub>
			<title-group>
				<article-title>Metas de Pressão Arterial: Chegaremos a um Número Definitivo? Neste
					Momento, Tenho o Meu</article-title>
			</title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Jardim</surname>
						<given-names>Paulo César B. Veiga</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/>
					<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2"/>
				</contrib>
				<aff id="aff2">
					<institution content-type="original">Faculdade de Medicina Universidade Federal
						de Goiás (UFG); Pós-graduação em Ciências da Saúde e Nutrição em Saúde da
						UFG; Liga de Hipertensão Arterial da UFG, Goiânia, GO - Brasil</institution>
				</aff>
			</contrib-group>
			<author-notes>
				<corresp id="c2"><bold>Correspondência: Paulo César B. Veiga Jardim,</bold> Rua
					115-F n 135, Setor Sul. CEP 74085-300, Goiania, GO - Brasil. E-mail:
						<email>fvjardim.ufg@gmail.com</email>, <email>fvjardim@terra.com.br</email>
				</corresp>
			</author-notes>
			<kwd-group xml:lang="pt">
				<title>Palavras-chave</title>
				<kwd>Hipertensão</kwd>
				<kwd>Pressão Arterial / fisiologia</kwd>
				<kwd>Anti-Hipertensivos</kwd>
				<kwd>Diabetes Mellitus</kwd>
				<kwd>Metas de Pressão Arterial</kwd>
			</kwd-group>
		</front-stub>
		<body>
			<p>Nasci na era da medicina sem evidências. Quando estudante, o diagnóstico de
				hipertensão arterial (HA) era feito a partir de valores de pressão arterial (PA)
				acima de 160/95 mmHg.</p>
			<p>Alguém pode imaginar isso agora?</p>
			<p>Na cardiologia avançamos demais, em todos os sentidos, tanto nos métodos de
				diagnóstico como na terapêutica. Hoje, o tratamento é baseado em evidências
				científicas e o arsenal de medicamentos é extremamente efetivo.</p>
			<p>Mas, voltemos à HA.</p>
			<p>Ao longo dos anos, aprendemos, através de um grande número de estudos, primeiro
				observacionais, depois de intervenção, que, se por um lado, o risco cardiovascular
				se eleva a partir de valores de 115/75 mmHg e dobra a cada aumento de 20 mmHg de
				pressão sistólica (PAS) e 10 mmHg de pressão diastólica (PAD), por outro, é
				diminuído de maneira significativa pela redução da PA, através do tratamento
				farmacológico oferecido aos hipertensos.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
					>1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
			<p>Não há evidências definitivas de que o tratamento não farmacológico (hábitos de vida
				saudáveis) dê os mesmos resultados, mas é um pressuposto tão óbvio, que é aceito
				universalmente, ainda que de difícil implementação no mundo em que vivemos.<xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5"
					>5</xref></p>
			<p>Excelentes fármacos anti-hipertensivos foram desenvolvidos e aperfeiçoados. Os
				benefícios de seu uso foram comprovados, tanto do ponto de vista da morbidade,
				quanto da mortalidade.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
			<p>Não paira qualquer dúvida sobre isso.</p>
			<p>Estamos envolvidos, entretanto, em diversos dilemas, a começar pelo acesso aos
				serviços de saúde e aos medicamentos, quando necessários. É um ponto crucial,
				depende de políticas públicas consistentes que mudem este estado de coisas, mas que
				não será objeto desta discussão.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
					>1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
			<p>Outro aspecto, no âmbito do tratamento propriamente dito, é o enorme desafio da
				adesão. Até hoje, uma minoria de indivíduos, mesmo conhecedores de sua situação de
				hipertensos e dos riscos inerentes a essa situação e, mesmo tendo acesso ao sistema
				de saúde, não adere ao tratamento proposto. Essa é outra grave questão que passa por
				medidas educacionais em todos os níveis, como principal forma de modificação desse
				comportamento, que é comum e universal, mas também não será hoje, objeto de minhas
					observações.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
			<p>E vamos ao ponto.</p>
			<p>Na medida em que, nos últimos 40 anos, centenas de estudos de tratamento de HA
				aconteceram ao redor do planeta, tivemos a oportunidade de constatar que a terapia
				farmacológica modifica a história natural da doença, diminuindo a mortalidade e a
				morbidade cardiovascular de maneira significativa. Deve ser destacado que tal fato
				ocorre, menos pelo tipo de fármaco utilizado, mas principalmente pela redução da
				PA.</p>
			<p>Fecha-se assim o ciclo epidemiológico, a redução dos valores de PA traz efetivamente
				o benefício.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B5">5</xref></p>
			<p>Mas, quanto devemos reduzir, até quanto é seguro?</p>
			<p>O dilema das metas!</p>
			<p>A maioria dos estudos que mostraram diminuição de eventos cardiovasculares foi
				desenhada para comparar valores de PA antes e depois do tratamento. No primeiro
				momento, fármacos ativos comparados a placebo, verificando as mudanças na PA e seus
				possíveis benefícios. Posteriormente, foram comparados medicamentos ativos entre si,
				na busca de diferenças entre eles.</p>
			<p>O foco principal não foi o nível de PA atingido, mas a diferença entre os valores
				iniciais e finais.</p>
			<p>Sabemos que a melhor fonte de evidências em medicina vem dos ensaios clínicos
				randomizados e controlados. Para o estabelecimento de metas objetivas era necessário
				que o desenho da investigação tivesse esse objetivo.</p>
			<p>O estudo HOT (<italic>Hypertension Optimal Treatment</italic>),<xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B6">6</xref> publicado em 1998, foi precursor em relação a metas. Nesse
				caso, a referência utilizada foi a PAD. Mais de 18.500 pacientes com idade entre 50
				e 80 anos (média 61,5 anos), com PAD entre 100 e 115 mmHg, foram alocados para metas
				de PAD &#x2264; 90 mmHg, PAD &#x2264; 85 mmHg e PAD &#x2264; 80 mmHg. Verificou-se
				que havia maior redução de eventos cardiovasculares na medida em que os valores
				obtidos eram menores, e o maior benefício ocorreu no grupo de pacientes que teve
				redução da PAD para um valor médio de 82,6 mmHg. Foi observado, ainda, que reduções
				abaixo desses valores eram seguras e que, entre os diabéticos, os benefícios foram
				ainda maiores para o grupo em que a meta era de PAD &#x2264; 80 mmHg. Esse estudo
				foi um marco no que diz respeito às metas de PA, e a diretrizes internacionais
				tomaram-no como base durante anos.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
					>1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">6</xref></p>
			<p>Tivemos, ao longo do tempo, centenas de investigações de intervenção medicamentosa,
				de boa qualidade, envolvendo milhares de pacientes e que continuaram sedimentando o
				conhecimento dos benefícios do controle da PA, mas, para avaliar metas, não tivemos
				tantos projetos.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6"
					>6</xref></p>
			<p>Muitos estarão pensando em alguns estudos que buscaram estabelecer metas, como o
				italiano Cardio-Sis publicado em 2009, que investigou hipertensos não diabéticos
				acima de 55 anos, e buscou metas de PAS &lt; 130 mmHg ou &lt;140 mmHg. Nesse, o
				desfecho primário de hipertrofia ventricular esquerda, que é intermediário, mostrou
				resultados significativamente favoráveis a valores inferiores de PA, sendo também
				encontrados resultados positivos em relação a desfechos secundários
				pré-especificados, esses, sim, cardiovasculares.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7"
					>7</xref></p>
			<p>Da mesma forma foi publicado em 2008 o CASE-J <italic>trial</italic>, que envolveu
				apenas idosos e indicou vantagens significativas para menores valores de PA. Ainda
				em 2008, o estudo JATOS também avaliou idosos e não mostrou diferenças entre metas
				menores que 140 mmHg ou 160 mmHg para PAS.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8"
					>8</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">9</xref></p>
			<p>Até então, todos os documentos oficiais (inclusive nossas últimas Diretrizes) sobre
				quais valores de PA deveriam ser buscados, para maiores benefícios, trabalhavam com
				níveis de PA menores que 140/90 mmHg para a população geral e menores que 130/80
				mmHg para os de alto risco cardiovascular, os com doença cardiovascular, os
				diabéticos e os com doença renal estabelecida.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1"
					>1</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">4</xref><sup>,</sup><xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">10</xref><sup>,</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11"
					>11</xref></p>
			<p>Em 2010, é publicado o resultado do Estudo ACCORD.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"
					>12</xref> Esse tratava exclusivamente de pacientes diabéticos e procurava
				definir, entre outras perguntas, se metas de controle da PA mais agressivas (PAS
				&lt; 120 mmHg) apresentavam alguma vantagem em relação a metas que foram definidas
				como convencionais (PAS &lt; 140 mmHg). Foram randomizados, para esse fim, mais de
				4.500 hipertensos diabéticos, com idade média de 62 anos, que foram seguidos por um
				período médio de 4,7 anos. O desfecho primário composto foi infarto do miocárdio não
				fatal, acidente vascular cerebral não fatal ou morte por causa cardiovascular. Foram
				também pré-definidos vários desfechos cardiocirculatórios secundários. Os resultados
				foram nulos, ou seja, não houve diferença nos eventos compostos cardiovasculares
				maiores, fatais e não fatais. No que diz respeito aos desfechos secundários, não
				houve diferença significativa em vários deles, mas, com relação ao acidente vascular
				fatal e não fatal, houve uma redução significativa desses eventos, de 41% e 37%
				respectivamente. O grupo de redução mais intensa da PA apresentou mais eventos
				adversos, mas sem comprometer o final do estudo.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12"
					>12</xref></p>
			<p>A repercussão desse estudo foi grande e trouxe, como consequência, um novo
				raciocínio, em minha avaliação, equivocado.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref>
				De modo quase que imediato, ficou subentendido que metas de PA mais rigorosas para
				diabéticos seriam prejudiciais, e, ainda de maneira indireta, houve um
				questionamento sobre metas de PA mais baixas para todos os tipos de pacientes.<xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">5</xref></p>
			<p>Avalio os achados do estudo ACCORD de maneira diferente e interpreto os resultados
				com outra ótica. Os desfechos primários foram semelhantes, ou seja, não houve
					diferença.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> E reforço, o significado
				disso é: não houve diminuição nem aumento dos eventos primários.<xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref></p>
			<p>Por outro lado, e não menos importante, ao verificarmos o desfecho secundário
				‘acidente vascular cerebral’, constatamos que houve benefícios para o grupo com
				controle mais intenso da PA.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">12</xref> Quem, em sã
				consciência, não quer proteger seu paciente diabético de um acidente vascular
				cerebral? Só para reflexão.</p>
			<p>Na sequência das investigações em busca dos valores mais adequados para a PA, no
				final de 2015 é publicado o estudo SPRINT.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref>
				Financiado pelo <italic>National Institutes of Health</italic> (NIH), sem qualquer
				conflito de interesses, o protocolo foi cuidadosamente desenhado com o objetivo
				específico de verificar quais valores de PA seriam mais benéficos em termos de
				desfechos cardiocirculatórios para pacientes hipertensos não diabéticos. Foram
				selecionados indivíduos de 50 anos ou mais, com PAS entre 130 e 180 mmHg e risco
				cardiovascular aumentado. Foram definidas metas de PAS &lt; 120 mmHg para os
				randomizados para tratamento mais intensivo, e PAS &lt; 140 mmHg para os indicados
				para tratamento definido como convencional. Os desfechos primários compostos foram
				infarto agudo do miocárdio, outras síndromes coronarianas agudas, acidente vascular
				cerebral, insuficiência cardíaca ou morte por causa cardiovascular. Os desfechos
				secundários foram definidos como os componentes individuais dos primários, morte por
				todas as causas e a soma do desfecho primário ou morte por todas as causas.<xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></p>
			<p>Foram randomizados 9.361 pacientes, sendo mais de 4.650 em cada modalidade de
				tratamento. A média de idade foi de 67,9 anos e os grupos foram homogêneos em todos
				os aspectos. No primeiro ano de seguimento, as médias alcançadas de PAS e PAD foram,
				respectivamente, de 121,4 e 68,7 mmHg no grupo de tratamento intensivo, e 136,2 e
				76,3 mmHg no grupo de tratamento convencional. Ao final do estudo, as médias das PAS
				foram de 121,5 e 134,6 mmHg, para o grupo de tratamento intensivo e convencional,
					respectivamente.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">13</xref></p>
			<p>O SPRINT, planejado para ter 5 anos de duração, foi interrompido pelo Comitê de
				Segurança aos 3,26 anos, por ter sido observada diferença significativa de desfechos
				entre os dois grupos, em dois momentos distintos pré-estabelecidos para esse
				controle. Houve uma diminuição de 25% nos desfechos primários no grupo de tratamento
				intensivo, e esta diferença já começou a aparecer a partir do primeiro ano da
				intervenção. O número de mortes por todas as causas foi também 27% menor no grupo de
				tratamento intensivo e, da mesma forma, ocorreram 43% menos mortes por causa
				cardiovascular nesse grupo de indivíduos. Os eventos adversos foram mais frequentes
				no grupo que teve controle mais rigoroso da PA sem, entretanto, haver prejuízos
				significativos que comprometessem o andamento da pesquisa.<xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B13">13</xref></p>
			<p>Esse ensaio clínico foi marcante, com um excelente desenho, objetivos claros e
				desenvolvimento correto. Seus resultados foram contundentes. Porém, como qualquer
				protocolo, sujeito a questionamentos. Nesse caso, a maioria sem consistência.</p>
			<p>Um ponto levantado foi o fato de ter sido interrompido antecipadamente.</p>
			<p>Mas, como não o fazer?</p>
			<p>Era uma questão de segurança. Como não oferecer o melhor aos pacientes? E revendo
				criticamente o estudo, sabe-se que seus resultados não podem ser questionados por
				esse motivo. De fato, o ensaio trouxe, efetivamente, preciosas informações sobre as
				metas a serem perseguidas.</p>
			<p>Uma boa alternativa aos ensaios clínicos randomizados, para a comprovação de
				evidências científicas, é oferecida pelas meta-análises e revisões sistemáticas. Mas
				sabemos que podem, também, ser levantados óbices aos seus resultados. Esses podem
				variar, na dependência dos critérios de seleção dos estudos que serão avaliados e de
				quais, finalmente, serão incluídos.</p>
			<p>No que diz respeito a metas de PA, temos um número razoável dessa modalidade de
				investigação.</p>
			<p>Destaco quatro trabalhos recentes nessa linha, sendo o primeiro de 2015, em pacientes
				diabéticos tipo 2, dois de 2016, sendo um de Xie et al.<xref ref-type="bibr"
					rid="B16">16</xref> e outro de Ettehad et al.,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15"
					>15</xref> que tratam de hipertensos em geral, e o último, publicado em 2017 no
				JACC, que avalia a mesma questão em pacientes idosos.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17"
					>17</xref> Todos demonstram os benefícios de controles mais rigorosos da PA como
				forma de diminuir a morbimortalidade cardiovascular dos pacientes.<xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">14</xref><sup>-</sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17"
					>17</xref></p>
			<p>Ainda com relação a essa questão, vale destacar o interessante editorial publicado
				por Perkovic e Rodgers,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">18</xref> no NEJM em novembro
				de 2015, quando da publicação do SPRINT. Nele, os autores fazem uma avaliação
				conjunta dos Estudos ACCORD e SPRINT, identificam suas semelhanças e eventuais
				diferenças e entendem os estudos como complementares, criando uma nova situação, com
				um número ainda maior de pacientes, e sugerindo resultados adicionais. Observam que
				ambos os estudos tinham a mesma meta de PA, os desfechos foram semelhantes, mas o
				estudo ACCORD teve um poder estatístico menor que o SPRINT, e alguns dos desfechos
				primários do ACCORD eram menos sensíveis às alterações da PA (<xref ref-type="fig"
					rid="f2">Figura 1</xref>). Esses autores não chegam a fazer uma sugestão
				objetiva de valores, mas indicam, com base em suas observações e convicções, que
				metas mais arrojadas são bem-vindas, principalmente para indivíduos de maior risco
				cardiovascular.</p>
			<p>
				<fig id="f2">
					<label>Figura 1</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Combinação dos desfechos do SPRINT e ACCORD e dados combinados dos
							dois estudos. IAM: infarto agudo do miocárdio; AVC: acidente vascular
							cerebral; ICC: Insufciência Cardíaca; ICo: eventos coronarianos; CV:
							cardiovascular. Adaptado de Perkovic e Rodgers.<xref ref-type="bibr"
								rid="B18">18</xref>
						</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:href="0066-782X-abc-109-01-0001-gf01-pt.tif"/>
				</fig>
			</p>
			<p>Por último, no início de 2017, Chobanian publica, no JAMA, um ponto de vista que
				coincide com meu pensamento.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref> Seu racional é
				bastante lógico com base nas evidências existentes até o momento. Sugere metas mais
				rigorosas (PA &lt; 120/80 mmHg) para indivíduos com menos de 50 anos. Valoriza,
				assim, a PAD nesse grupo, reforçando o conceito da importância da PAD para os mais
				jovens. Sugere valores menores que 130 mmHg para todos aqueles entre 50 e 74 anos
				com risco cardiovascular elevado ou com doença estabelecida, inclusive os
				diabéticos, considerando os benefícios oferecidos pelo ACCORD em relação ao acidente
				vascular cerebral. Finalmente reserva valores &lt; 140 mmHg para todos os pacientes
				com idade igual ou maior que 75 anos.<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">19</xref></p>
			<p>Mesmo levando em conta a falta de informações definitivas sobre quais números devem
				ser buscados em pacientes de alto risco cardiovascular, inclusive com algumas
				inferências de que valores excessivamente baixos possam ser prejudiciais,<xref
					ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">20</xref> esses são os números com os quais tenho
				trabalhado, levando em conta, evidentemente, a peculiaridade de cada paciente.</p>
			<p>Por fim, devemos ter em mente que a maioria dos indivíduos permanece com níveis de PA
				muito acima de qualquer meta estabelecida e aceitar valores mais elevados, ser
				contemplativo, é prejudicial e representará, ao longo dos anos, um recrudescimento
				significativo das doenças cardiovasculares que ainda são a principal causa de
				morbidade e mortalidade nos dias atuais.</p>
		</body>
	</sub-article>
</article>
