<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article
  PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "http://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.0/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
	article-type="case-report" dtd-version="1.0" specific-use="sps-1.6" xml:lang="en">
	<front>
		<journal-meta>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Arq Bras Cardiol</journal-id>
			<journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">abc</journal-id>
			<journal-title-group>
				<journal-title>Arquivos Brasileiros de Cardiologia</journal-title>
				<abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Arq. Bras.
					Cardiol.</abbrev-journal-title>
			</journal-title-group>
			<issn pub-type="ppub">0066-782X</issn>
			<issn pub-type="epub">1678-4170</issn>
			<publisher>
				<publisher-name>Sociedade Brasileira de Cardiologia - SBC</publisher-name>
			</publisher>
		</journal-meta>
		<article-meta>
			<article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.5935/abc.20170077</article-id>
			<article-categories>
				<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
					<subject>Image</subject>
				</subj-group>
			</article-categories>
			<title-group>
				<article-title>Angiosarcoma Arising from the Main Pulmonary Artery Mimicking
					Pulmonary Thromboembolism</article-title>
			</title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Ferreira</surname>
						<given-names>Joana Sofia Silva Moura</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
					<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c1"/>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Moreira</surname>
						<given-names>Nádia</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Ferreira</surname>
						<given-names>Maria João</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Antunes</surname>
						<given-names>Manuel</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/>
				</contrib>
				<aff id="aff1">
					<institution content-type="orgname">Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de
						Coimbra</institution>
					<country country="PT">Portugal</country>
					<institution content-type="original">Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de
						Coimbra, Portugal</institution>
				</aff>
			</contrib-group>
			<author-notes>
				<corresp id="c1"><bold>Mailing Address: Joana Sofia Silva Moura Ferreira</bold>, Rua
					do Padrão, 479, Vila Maior, Coimbra - Portugal. E-mail:
						<email>joanasofia.moura@gmail.com</email>,
						<email>joanasofia_moura@hotmail.com</email>
				</corresp>
				<fn fn-type="con">
					<p><bold>Author contributions</bold></p>
					<p>Conception and design of the research: Ferreira JSSM; Writing of the
						manuscript: Ferreira JSSM, Moreira N; Supervision: Ferreira MJ, Antunes
						M.</p>
				</fn>
				<fn fn-type="conflict">
					<p><bold>Potential Conflict of Interest</bold></p>
					<p>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was reported.</p>
				</fn>
			</author-notes>
			<pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
				<month>07</month>
				<year>2017</year>
			</pub-date>
			<volume>109</volume>
			<issue>1</issue>
			<fpage>90</fpage>
			<lpage>91</lpage>
			<history>
				<date date-type="received">
					<day>17</day>
					<month>10</month>
					<year>2016</year>
				</date>
				<date date-type="rev-recd">
					<day>27</day>
					<month>10</month>
					<year>2016</year>
				</date>
				<date date-type="accepted">
					<day>27</day>
					<month>10</month>
					<year>2016</year>
				</date>
			</history>
			<permissions>
				<license license-type="open-access"
					xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/" xml:lang="en">
					<license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the
						Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use,
						distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is
						properly cited.</license-p>
				</license>
			</permissions>
			<kwd-group xml:lang="en">
				<title>Keywords</title>
				<kwd>Echocardiography</kwd>
				<kwd>Pulmonary Embolism</kwd>
				<kwd>Thoracic Surgery</kwd>
			</kwd-group>
		</article-meta>
	</front>
	<body>
		<p>A 79-year-old female with no relevant past medical history was admitted in our emergency
			department for dyspnea on minimal exertion and chest discomfort over 2 weeks. Blood gas
			analysis showed severe hypoxemia and hypocapnia. Troponin was slightly positive. Despite
			a negative D-dimer assay, contrast-enhanced chest CT was performed to exclude pulmonary
			embolism. It showed a large filling defect centered in the pulmonary valve plane (Panels
			A and B). Bedside transthoracic echocardiogram showed a large echodense mass, apparently
			mobile, extending across the right ventricle outflow tract, pulmonary valve, and the
			main pulmonary artery, with dilatation of the right sided chambers and transtricuspid
			peak gradient of 70 mmHg (Panels C and D). Lower-limb venous compression ultrasound was
			negative for deep vein thrombosis. The patient remained stable, but required high oxygen
			inspiration fraction to maintain saturation above 90%. As pulmonary embolism was deemed
			unlikely given the clinical findings, the patient underwent cardiac surgery. Surgery
			revealed a pearly mass in the main pulmonary artery obliterating almost the entire lumen
			and with upstream extension to the pulmonary valve and right ventricle outflow tract
			(Panel E). The tumor was excised as much as possible and the pulmonary valve was
			replaced by a homograft. Pathological examination was compatible with angiosarcoma.</p>
		<p>Pulmonary artery angiosarcoma is exceedingly rare and carries a very poor prognosis. It
			can be clinical and radiologically indistinguishable from acute or chronic pulmonary
			artery thromboembolism. Our clinical suspicion was heightened by a negative D-dimer
			assay and venous ultrasound and the apparent infiltration of pulmonary arterial walls on
			CT.</p>
		<p>
			<fig id="f1">
				<label>Figure 1</label>
				<caption>
					<title>Angiosarcoma.</title>
				</caption>
				<graphic xlink:href="0066-782X-abc-109-01-0090-gf01.png"/>
			</fig>
		</p>
	</body>
	<back>
		<fn-group>
			<fn fn-type="supported-by">
				<p><bold>Sources of Funding</bold></p>
				<p>There were no external funding sources for this study.</p>
			</fn>
			<fn fn-type="other">
				<p><bold>Study Association</bold></p>
				<p>This study is not associated with any thesis or dissertation work.</p>
			</fn>
		</fn-group>
	</back>
	<sub-article article-type="translation" id="s1" xml:lang="pt">
		<front-stub>
			<article-categories>
				<subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
					<subject>Imagem</subject>
				</subj-group>
			</article-categories>
			<title-group>
				<article-title>Angiossarcoma no Tronco Pulmonar Imitando Tromboembolismo
					Pulmonar</article-title>
			</title-group>
			<contrib-group>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Ferreira</surname>
						<given-names>Joana Sofia Silva Moura</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/>
					<xref ref-type="corresp" rid="c2"/>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Moreira</surname>
						<given-names>Nádia</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Ferreira</surname>
						<given-names>Maria João</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/>
				</contrib>
				<contrib contrib-type="author">
					<name>
						<surname>Antunes</surname>
						<given-names>Manuel</given-names>
					</name>
					<xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/>
				</contrib>
				<aff id="aff2">
					<institution content-type="original">Centro Hospitalar e Universitário de
						Coimbra, Portugal</institution>
				</aff>
			</contrib-group>
			<author-notes>
				<corresp id="c2"><bold>Correspondência: Joana Sofia Silva Moura Ferreira</bold>, Rua
					do Padrão, 479, Vila Maior, Coimbra - Portugal. E-mail:
						<email>joanasofia.moura@gmail.com</email>,
						<email>joanasofia_moura@hotmail.com</email>
				</corresp>
				<fn fn-type="con">
					<p><bold>Contribuição dos autores</bold></p>
					<p>Concepção e desenho da pesquisa: Ferreira JSSM; Redação do manuscrito:
						Ferreira JSSM, Moreira N; Supervisão: Ferreira MJ, Antunes M.</p>
				</fn>
				<fn fn-type="conflict">
					<p><bold>Potencial conflito de interesses</bold></p>
					<p>Declaro não haver conflito de interesses pertinentes.</p>
				</fn>
			</author-notes>
			<kwd-group xml:lang="pt">
				<title>Palavras-chave</title>
				<kwd>Ecocardiografia</kwd>
				<kwd>Embolia Pulmonar</kwd>
				<kwd>Cirurgia Torácica</kwd>
			</kwd-group>
		</front-stub>
		<body>
			<p>Uma mulher de 79 anos de idade, sem histórico médico passado relevante, foi internada
				em nosso departamento de emergência devido a dispneia com esforço mínimo e
				desconforto torácico que perdurava há 2 semanas. A análise da gasometria sanguínea
				mostrou hipoxemia e hipocapnia graves. A troponina estava ligeiramente positiva.
				Apesar do teste de dímero-D ter sido negativo, foi realizada TC com contraste para
				excluir embolia pulmonar. Ela mostrou um grande defeito de preenchimento centrado no
				plano da válvula pulmonar (Painéis A e B). O ecocardiograma transtorácico à beira do
				leito mostrou uma grande massa ecodensa, aparentemente móvel, estendendo-se através
				da via de saída do ventrículo direito, válvula pulmonar e tronco pulmonar, com
				dilatação das câmaras do lado direito e gradiente transtricúspide de pico de 70 mmHg
				(Painéis C e D). O ultrassom de compressão venosa dos membros inferiores foi
				negativo para trombose venosa profunda. A paciente manteve-se estável mas necessitou
				de fração de inspiração de oxigênio elevada para manter a saturação acima de 90%.
				Como a embolia pulmonar foi considerada improvável, devido aos achados clínicos, a
				paciente foi submetida à cirurgia cardíaca. A cirurgia revelou uma massa perolada na
				artéria pulmonar principal obliterando quase todo o lúmen e com extensão a montante
				para a válvula pulmonar e via de saída do ventrículo direito (Painel E). O tumor foi
				excisado tanto quanto possível e a válvula pulmonar foi substituída por um
				homoenxerto. O exame patológico foi compatível com angiossarcoma.</p>
			<p>O angiossarcoma da artéria pulmonar é extremamente raro e tem um prognóstico muito
				ruim. Pode ser clínico e radiologicamente indistinguível do tromboembolismo agudo ou
				crônico da artéria pulmonar. Nossa suspeita clínica foi aumentada pelo teste
				negativo de dímero D e ultrassom venoso, e a aparente infiltração de paredes
				arteriais pulmonares na TC.</p>
			<p>
				<fig id="f2">
					<label>Figura 1</label>
					<caption>
						<title>Angiosarcoma.</title>
					</caption>
					<graphic xlink:href="0066-782X-abc-109-01-0090-gf01-pt.png"/>
				</fig>
			</p>
		</body>
		<back>
			<fn-group>
				<fn fn-type="supported-by">
					<p><bold>Fontes de financiamento</bold></p>
					<p>O presente estudo não teve fontes de financiamento externas.</p>
				</fn>
				<fn fn-type="other">
					<p><bold>Vinculação acadêmica</bold></p>
					<p>Não há vinculação deste estudo a programas de pós-graduação.</p>
				</fn>
			</fn-group>
		</back>
	</sub-article>
</article>
